Guide to the Phillips Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Phillips family papers
1901-2010
MS 1927
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14.13
(15 boxes)
The collection comprises correspondence, vital records, family histories and reminiscences, photographs and other material concerning the lives and work of several generations of members of the Phillips, Rubinstein, Levine, and Sussman families of the New York area. The collection is especially strong in documentation of the extended personal and business relationships of several prosperous Jewish families in the New York City area during the twentieth century.
Phillips family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Christopher Phillips, Adam Phillips, David F. Phillips, and Victoria L. Phillips, 2004. Gift of David F. Phillips, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Associated Materials
Christopher Phillips Papers (MS 1830). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises correspondence, vital records, family histories and reminiscences, photographs and other material concerning the lives and work of several generations of members of the Phillips, Rubinstein, Levine, and Sussman families of the New York area. The collection is especially strong in documentation of the extended personal and business relationships of several prosperous Jewish families in the New York City area during the twentieth century.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel J. Phillips (1916-1973) and Nina David Rubinstein Phillips (1917-1980) were married in New York City on 14 May 1942. They had four children: David (born 1944), Christopher (born 1950), Victoria (born 1955), and Adam (born 1955).
Arrangement
Arranged by the donor by name of family member and by type of material.
Jewish families -- New York (State) -- New York; Jewish families; Levin family; Phillips family; Rubinstein family; Sussman family
- Family histories
  - The Phillips Story: A Chronicle and Documentary Record by Lucjan Dobroszycki, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Included here is a photocopy, parts of which are difficult to read. The original is probably in the Phillips Ambulatory Care Center of Beth Israel Hospital, Union Square, Manhattan. There are several inaccuracies and inconsistencies in this account.
  - Phillips family tree, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Contains inaccuracies, with some corrections by Christopher Phillips.
  - The Rubinstein Family Photo Archive and Catalog, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Document compiled and produced by Christopher Phillips. It includes photographs (photocopied) and relevant life dates of all the children of Jacob and Nettie Rubinstein, with lists of their descendants, including addresses (complete up to 1998). It also contains explanatory notes about Plungyan (present-day Plunge), Lithuania.
  - The Rubinstein Family Genealogy, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Document compiled in 1993 by Esther Roth Rubinstein (wife of Martin Rubinstein, son of Harry Rubinstein). According to Christopher Phillips it seems accurate about the descendants of Harry Rubinstein, but has inaccuracies regarding other branches of the family.
- Phillips, Samuel J. (1916-1973)
  - Writings and artwork, 1920-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes childhood writings and cartoons on a page that also contains Nina David Phillips's characteristic doodles that she would do while on the telephone. Also contains a watercoloring done on a 19th-century newspaper engraving (color photocopy) and reviews written for The Beacon, the newsletter of the Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Huntington, New York; the original manuscript and published copy of an article "It and the Technician;" and an article from the January/February 1974 issue of the journal Radiologic Technology, which explains Samuel J. Phillips's philosophy of dealing with patients as people, to have an "I-you" relationship rather than an "I-it" relationship with them.
  - The Franklinite, 1928, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    Yearbook of Franklin School, New York, NY.
  - Letters from his mother, 1928-1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    At least one telegram (1924) from his father, David F. Phillips I.
  - School reports and other material, Circa 1931-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes British visiting cards, copies of school prizes and other childhood memorabilia.
  - Military records, Circa 1941-1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Contains his 1941 application to Naval Reserve with a complete résumé of his schooling and work history. Also has notes Christopher Phillips took in 1982 on the site of former Fort Dupont in Delaware City, Delaware.
  - Cards and notes, Circa 1950-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Cards and notes between him and Nina Phillips.
  - Wedding documentation, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes telegrams and a photograph of Morty Herskovits, the best man of the wedding. Also the July 1942 issue of The Target, the newsletter of the Auxiliary Aircraft Warning Service, New York, with a mention of the marriage.
  - Medical school student papers, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    School papers and relics, including class photograph.
  - Medical Violet, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Yearbook of New York University College of Medicine.
  - Medical licenses and diplomas, Circa 1950-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wallets and cards, Circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    From the time of Samuel J. Phillips's death.
  - Passports and documents, Circa 1936-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes passports, birth certificate and other documents. Also has an envelope of cards and other scraps of paper found in his desk at the time of his death.
  - Death and memorial service, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Death and memorial service at Community Church in Manhattan. Includes notes, eulogies (by Rev. Ralph Stutsman and David F. Phillips II), mention in a column of The Provincetown Advocate newspaper. Also contains program from dedication of the Sam Phillips Memorial Garden at the Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Huntington, N.Y.
  - Various materials related to the life of Samuel J. Phillips, Circa 1953-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Issue of Forefront, the newsletter of Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center from January 1970 with his photograph and description of new radiology facilities (photocopy). Contains medical résumé; University Hospital bill from first heart attack (24 Dec 1967 to 27 Jan 1968); columns by Tom Kane from The Provincetown Advocate; list of degrees and medical licenses; letter from Samuel J. Phillips to T. Margaret Jamer, 17 Aug 1967 following a trip to Ireland; material about an anti-stuttering metronome ordered from Scotland, 1967; addresses of rented houses in Westchester, summers 1957-1959; Memorial Hospital stationery; photocopy of cover of The Forgotten Peninsula by Joseph Wood Krutch; and scraps and notes.
- Phillips, Nina David (nee Rubinstein, 1917-1980)
  - Berkely Institute (Brooklyn, N.Y.) yearbooks, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters with childhood reminiscences, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Letter written on the death of her uncle, Abraham Rubinstein, containing reminiscences of her childhood, and of Abraham and Esther Rubinstein.
  - Sightseeing boat, New York harbor, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes her script, an article in The New York World-Telegram about her, a transcript of a Kate Smith broadcast discussing her, photographs of the boat and crew, and the Manual for Lifeboatmen and Able Seamen (U.S. Department of Commerce, 1937).
  - Wartime diary, 1942-1944 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    In this document, she describes her life as a military wife as she set up home for herself and Samuel J. Phillips in towns where he was posted (photocopy of 202 handwritten pages).
  - Date books, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Address books, Circa 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Various materials related to the life of Nina David Phillips, Circa 1917-1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes a document from WNET Channel 13 in New York; photographs and correspondence from college friends, especially Basia McCoy (née Barbara Kocyan); childhood letter to her mother; 1939 newsletter from camp where she was counselor. Also November 1942 issue of "The Target," newsletter of the Aircraft Warning Service, with an article on Nina Phillips's engagement; photocopies of covers and flyleaves of some of her favorite books (Edna St. Vincent Millay and others).
  - School Volunteers
    A public education program administered by the Public Education Association, New York City.
    - Writings and newsletters, 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes copies of "School Volunteer News" and various documents, including "The Chairman and the Program," a 22-page manual written by Nina Phillips and other memos by her. Includes Christian Science Monitor article that mentions her, and "School Volunteer News" from June 1966 with article about her resignation.
    - "Child and the Program", Circa 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Personal training manual and writings for volunteer orientation, especially on the "culture of poverty." Includes written comments by T. Margaret Jamer (known as Jimmie Jamer).
    - School Volunteer News, 1959-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Jamer, T. Margaret, School Volunteers: Creating a New Dimension in Education through Lay Participation, New York: Public Education Association, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Inscribed by the author to Nina Phillips. Also included is a copy of "School Volunteer News" with a valedictory tribute to Miss Jamer, probably written by Nina Phillips.
  - Phillips, Nina, Conversational English for the Non-English-Speaking Child: An Audio-Visual-Lingual Approach to English as a Second Language, with Special Emphasis on the Needs of the Disadvantaged Child, New York: Teachers College Press (third printing), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Earlier printings were spiral bound.
  - Letters to her in hospital, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 12-15)
    Many from WNET Channel 13 volunteers.
  - Memorial service and reminiscences, Circa 1980-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Program from memorial service, biographical notes, and personal reminiscences from various friends.
  - Birth certificate, passport, and other material, 1917-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jamer, Jimmie (T. Margaret), letters from, Circa 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
  - Travel diaries, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8-14)
    Photocopies of travel diaries written by T. Margaret (Jimmie) Jamer chronicling trips taken with Nina Phillips.
- Residences, collections, and financial affairs of Samuel J. Phillips and Nina David Phillips
  - 1136 Fifth Avenue, 1945-1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Photographs of interior before and after the collection of 18th-century antique furniture was amassed, fabric swatches, and floor plan of the apartment drawn by David F. Phillips in 1999.
  - 112 East 70th Street, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Photographs of the brownstone, constructed circa 1878, in 1954 (before renovation) and in 1956 (after renovation); interior and exterior photographs.
  - 112 East 70th Street, Circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Photographs of the interior taken after Nina David Phillips's death.
  - Truro, Massachusetts house, Circa 1969-1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Contains photographs of the house in the 1960s and 1980s, including aerial views of this part of the Cape Cod National Seashore. Also has a receipt for a canoe, called the Swamp Swallow, and a flyer from 1988 for sale of the house.
  - Antiques, Circa 1960-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Photographs of antique furniture and pottery, and Nina David Phillips's inventory notebook of pottery and porcelain purchases. Includes a catalogue from an exhibition at Metropolitan Museum of Art in which one of the Phillips's chairs appeared. Lastly, includes "Opulence and Splendor: The New York Chair, 1690-1830," a 1984 booklet published by Bernard & S. Dean Levy Inc., in which some Phillips's chairs appeared.
  - Antiques - Sotheby's, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    Sotheby's catalogue from the sale of most of the Phillips furniture, Fine Americana auction of 26 September 1981. Included is Christopher Phillips's list of Phillips's lots in the sale. Sotheby's newsletter for September 1981 with photograph of a Phillips piece. Catalogue from Sotheby's Fine American Furniture and Related Decorative Arts sale, April 1981 (Phillips's lots, mostly for pottery, are noted in catalogue); Sotheby's English Furniture and Ceramics auction catalogue, 19 December 1981 (Phillips's lots are 17 through 25).
  - Household ephemera, Circa 1950-1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Includes stationery of Nina David Phillips, checklists, photographs of 112 East 70th Street, and a sketch of floorplan of 112 East 70th Street by Christopher Phillips in 2008.
  - Checks and checkbooks, 1952-1957 (Box 4, Folder 4-12)
  - Checks and checkbooks, 1954-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Checkbooks, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
  - Checks and checkbooks, 1964-1969 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
  - Checkbooks and financial records, 1966-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1-10)
  - Checks and checkbooks, 1974-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
- Phillips, David F. II (born 1944), son of Samuel and Nina Phillips
  - An account of his birth, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Photocopy of an account of his birth written by his grandmother, Ida J. Rubinstein, in a letter to her son, Roy M. Rubinstein.
  - The Dutchman yearbooks and card, 1954-1956 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    Yearbooks from Collegiate School and an anniversary card to his parents.
  - Letters to Noah Phillips, 1998 - 2004 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    Letters with illustrations from David to his nephew, Samuel Noah Phillips (born 1992).
  - Various materials relating to the life of David F. Phillips II, 1971-2002 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Statement written as reunion information for Columbia College Alumni Association, Penn Law School commencement program, and deed of gift of heraldic items to Museum of the City of New York.
  - "How to Avoid Getting Sick in the Third World" and "Looking at the Emblems of the Indian States," writings by David F. Phillips II, Circa 1990-2008 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Autobiography manuscript: "What I Remember About My Life" by David F. Phillips., 2010
    - Preface and Chapters 1 to 3A (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 3B to 11 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 12 to 17 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 18 to 21 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 22 to 26 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Chapters 27A to 29 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Chapters 30 to 35 (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Phillips, Louise (1912-1955)
  - Material documenting her childhood, Circa 1920-1925 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Notes, some illustrated, to her parents, illustrated story books written by Louise, and drawings.
  - Artwork in books, 1946-1951 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
    Books with illustrations by Louise Phillips: Oscar Wilde, The Ballad of Reading Goal and Other Poems (New York: Greystone Press, 1951); Oscar Wilde, The Happy Prince and Other Tales (New York: Greystone Press, 1951); Russell McCracken, The Sound of Sleigh Bells (New York: Farrar, Straus and Young, 1951); Louise Phillips, French for Peter, (London: Art and Educational Publishers Ltd., 1946).
  - Artwork on cloth, Circa 1940-1955 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    Color photocopy of an original in the possession of Christopher Phillips.
  - Drawings, sketches, and watercolors, Circa 1921-1955 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Includes some photocopies of originals in the possession of Christopher Phillips.
  - 17 Commerce Street, 1932-1955 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    Drawing of her house at 17 Commerce Street (not by Louise) as it appeared in The Villager, a local Greenwich Village newspaper; a Schumacher sample of the wallpaper used in the dining room at 17 Commerce Street ("Pudden Hill" pattern); photostats of her Mexican divorce decree; and the closing letter from sale of 17 Commerce Street.
  - Financial records, 1952-1965 (Box 9, Folder 16-19)
    Contains her will, correspondence about her estate, bankbook, checkbooks, and scraps of paper referring to financial affairs.
  - Checkbooks and records relating to her trust and estate, 1955 - 1969 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
- Rubinstein, Roy M. (1912-1993)
  - Childhood keepsake album, Circa 1912-1930 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Includes letters from his father, letters to his parents, and two letters from Fresh Meadow Country Club. There is also his Bar Mitzvah speech, articles he saved, and other keepsakes.
  - Materials documenting his later life, Circa 1960-1993 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    Includes statistical notes on the financial markets, two photographs of Constance Keene kept in his bedroom, photographs of his apartment just after his death, and other memorabilia.
  - Various materials relating to the life of Roy M. Rubinstein, 1934-1955 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    Consists of employment applications, with detailed résumés, birth certificate, University of Pennsylvania diploma, and a photocopy of a University of Pennsylvania yearbook page.
- Rubinstein, David Lazarus (1888-1929)
  - Letter regarding his marriage, 1911 June 7 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    From David to his sister Ida (1883-1969, later Gittelson) describing the wedding, typed transcription.
  - Correspondence, 1916-1927 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Exchange of letters with his brother Morris in 1916 and postcard to Ida J. Rubinstein from Italy, 1927.
  - Business dealings, 1926-1929 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    Contracts and correspondence relating to the Textile Yarn Company, negotiations with S.B. and B.W. Fleischer yarn manufacturers of Philadelphia, and announcement of the Knitwear Manufacturers League of New York.
  - Correspondence and resolutions relating to his death, 1929-1939 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    Includes photostat of death certificate.
  - Shore, Josselyn M., The Story of the Fresh Meadow Country Club, New York: Fresh Meadow Country Club, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    Privately published book that mentions David L. Rubinstein among the founders (page 20).
- Rubinstein, Ida J. (nee Sussman, 1890-1962)
  - Passports, datebooks, address books, and other material, 1912-1965 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    Includes some imperial Russian 500 ruble banknotes dated 1912.
  - Financial records, Circa 1901-1965 (Box 11, Folder 3-7)
    Includes stock certificates, leases, insurance certificates, correspondence, ledgers, and other material.
  - Letters from Ida J. Rubinstein to her daughter Nina Phillips, Circa 1930-1935 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Probably written during Nina's college years, includes a Wedding Day letter from Nina to her mother.
  - Wartime correspondence between Ida Rubinstein and her family members, 1942-1944 (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
    Predominantly correspondence with Roy M. Rubinstein and Nina and Samuel Phillips.
  - Letters and cards to family, Circa 1954-1955 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    These are mostly from Europe, but also from Florida and elsewhere.
  - Cards from hospital stay, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Memorabilia, Circa 1930-1962 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Contains cards, a London theater program, lists, stationery, and Ida's own envelope marked "Things Past."
  - Reminiscences, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    Short reminiscences of her by Nate Levine, son of Sarah Rubinstein Levine, and Blanche Gould, the wife of Sidney Gould (Ida's nephew).
- Phillips, David F. I (1880 - 1925), notation on envelope of Bank of the United States shares owned by his estate, Circa 1925 (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Phillips, Beatrice Silberman (later Weiner, 1888-1932) material, 1925-1965 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  Comprises a sketch of her grave in London made by Christopher Phillips, a letter to Samuel J. Phillips from St. John's Wood Liberal Cemetery in London, and a certificate from Beth Israel Hospital to commemorate the naming of a room for her parents.
- Phillips, Isaac L. (1870-1923) and descendants
  - Phillips, Libby M., diary, 1914-1916 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    Transcription of her diary, with explanatory notes by her grandson Gary Marcus.
  - Green, Douglas, promotional video for Green Furniture Design Company, Inc. (Portland, Maine), 1995 April; 1; Commercially produced videotape (VHS), approximately 10 minutes. (Box 14)
    Green is the son of Carol Green Nash, née Phillips, daughter of Isaac's son Seymour.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository.
  - Phillips, Lawrence S., New York Times article, "The Last Phillips Retires From Phillips-Van Heusen", 1995 February 15 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Silberman Family, S.J.S. Associates documents, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Consists of partnership papers and amendments relating to SJS Associates, a family limited partnership in which various descendants of Samuel J. Silberman had shares.
- Blaut, Stephan (son of Florence Silberman Blaut, circa 1918 - 1979) and family
  - Stephan Blaut, Circa 1929-1979 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Obituary in The New York Times and a postcard to Beatrice Silberman Phillips with a picture of Stephan standing near the French statesman Briand.
  - Blaut, Julia (later DeWees, daughter of Stephan), photocopy of a holiday card with photographs of her children (Nina, Sam, Jake), 2007 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Marks Family
  - Marks family tree, handwritten, probably by Jack Marks, Circa 1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Marks, Jack, announcements of the annual Marks Memorial Lecture at the University of Arizona College of Law, 1995-2008 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Rubinstein, Jacob (circa 1855 to circa 1930) naturalization certificate, 1903-1998 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  Includes memories of Jacob Rubinstein by his grandson Nate Levine (son of Sarah Rubinstein Levine).
- Rubinstein, Abraham (1889-1974) and descendants scrapbook album, Circa 1973 (Box 13)
- Rubinstein, Harry (1880-1955) textile patent and letter on Rubinstein relations, Circa 1930-1994 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Gittelson, Ida (nee Rubinstein, 1883-1969) newspaper article with photograph of her Flatbush house, Circa 1990-2000 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Hoffman, Naomi (nee Gittelson, later Siegel, later Hoffman, daughter of Ida Gittelson) material, 1978-1997 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  Essay on her by her son, Dan Siegel, and letter from her to her aunt, Sarah Levine (née Rubinstein).
- Siegel, Judge Kenneth M. (son of Naomi, 1945-1997), newspaper articles about him, 1985-1997 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Siegel, Julie (born 1983, daughter of Dan Siegel), invitation to her M.S.W. graduation from UCLA, 2006 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Berson, Miriam (nee Gittelson, 1913-1995) material, Circa 1972-1980 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  Essay, "Sol Berson, the Man," written by her about her husband, Dr. Solomon A. Berson (1918-1972), who was a colleague of Nobel laureate Rosalyn S. Yalow in medical research. Also tributes to Sol Berson in The Ligand Review.
- Rubinstein, Morris (1878-1947) and descendants reminiscences, 1998 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  By Nate Levine (son of Sarah Rubinstein Levine), his nephew.
- Rubinstein, Nathan (1885-1915) letters to his sister Sarah (later Levine), 1914-1915 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  Photocopies of original letters in the possession of Nate Levine.
- Levine, Nate (born 1919) reminiscences, 1998-2006 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  Son of Sarah Levine (née Rubinstein, 1891-1980), reminscences about Rubinstein family members and correspondence with David F. Phillips about Nate's tenure as head of the Walden School high school in New York.